なんば　むった
(南波六太)＜外の世界とは完全に
切り離された➡
It's been five days since we first began living inside
the sealed boxes that separate us from the outside world.
へいさ
閉鎖ボックスでの生活が
始まってから５日目＞
I never expected them to monitor us during our free time.
＜まさか自由時間まで しっかり
かんし
監視されてるとはつゆ知らず＞
Make a face and hold it...
If you laugh, you lose!
笑うと負けよ アップップ！
(古谷)むうぅ…フ～｡
(六太)むむむ…む～！
(古谷)むむ…にに…｡
ウキーッ！
ぶふっ わっはっはは…！
よっしゃあ！２勝目！
Yes! That makes two wins!
《なんて面白い顔だ》
That was a hilarious face.
新田は にらめっこ
やらんでええんか？➡
You wanna join in, Nitta?
プリンもらうぞ～｡
There's pudding on the line.
(新田)フン…プリンならやるよ｡
You can have mine.
(福田)じゃあ最後に僕が｡
I guess I'm the last one.
Okay, let's do this.
よっしゃ ほないくで｡せ～の！
Ready, and...
ぬぐぐ…｡
(せりか)ウフフ…｡
フフ…福田さん｡
Fukuda...
ハハハ…！アカン！➡
Crap!
なんやおっちゃん そんな武器
隠し持っとったんか！
That's a lethal weapon you have, old timer...
にらめっこは得意でね｡
プリンはいただきだな｡
I'm good at making funny faces.
That means I get your pudding.
凄いですね 福田さん｡
That was incredible, Fukuda...
顔の筋肉動きすぎやで ホンマ｡
Your face can really twist!
《福田直人 恐るべき５４歳》
Fukuda Naoto,
a fearsome fifty-four year old.
I will rise,
climb,
and shoot through the atmosphere
My goal is zero gravity
Space Brothers
Waves of people flood the intersection
Like vague silhouettes they stream past incessantly
How do I look in their midst?
I don't know
Hiding my true intentions desperately
I dish out vague excuses
My ambitions of going to space, harbored for so long,
are frail and brittle
No matter how I turn the globus
I have no home where I end up
There's no point to looking on a map
I will rise,
climb,
and shoot through the atmosphere
until I can look down on the entire world
I will yell
and scream
with a heart of steel
that I am going to zero gravity
14 Years Ago
#14 Broken Glasses and
the Sole of the Foot
(福田)代わってくれよ 涼子に｡
Put Ryoko on.
電話で話すぐらい構わないだろ？
I'm allowed to talk to her
by phone, right?
No, you promised you'd never see her again.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](福田の元妻)
ダメよ｡
もう会わない約束でしょ｡➡
今さら父親ぶらないでよ｡
It's too late to act like a father now.
頼むよ｡今度の打ち上げは➡
I'm begging you...
They're going to launch the rocket I was in charge of designing.
私が総指揮を務める
ロケットなんだ｡
(福田)涼子に見せたい｡
きっと感動する｡
I want to show Ryoko!
I'm sure she'll be impressed!
[ｹｲﾀｲ]ハァ…ほら｡
See?
[ｹｲﾀｲ]結局 それも仕事の話｡
It's always about your work.
相変わらず
全然わかってないわ あなた｡
You still don't understand.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](福田)いや だってこれは…｡
涼子ね 陰山さんのこと最近➡
No, this is...
Ryoko has
started calling Kageyama "Dad".
Apple.
お父さんって呼ぶように
なってきたのよ｡
[ｹｲﾀｲ]だからもう ジャマしないで｡
Huh?
So don't try to interfere.
現在
ハァ～…｡
Oops.
(福田)おっと｡
おう おっちゃん｡
Hey, old timer...
Eh?
(茄子田)まあ ５日目とも
なるとねぇ➡
So, after five days, we've been able to identify each team's personality?
各班に性格が
現れてきたみたいね｡
Yes.
(試験官)ええ｡Ｃ班は 穏やか｡
Ａ班は にぎやか｡➡
Team C is quiet.
Team A is rowdy.
びみょう
けんあく
Ｂ班は 微妙に険悪な
ムードが漂っています｡
And Team B is looking a little gloomy right now.
Oh, dear...
あららら…｡そうなの？
Really?
各班の行動範囲と移動距離を
合計したグラフです｡
These graphs chart each team's range and frequency of movement.
Ｂ班だけが こんなに
活動量が落ちていますよ｡
Only Team B's indicates a decrease.
ふ～ん｡
Hmm....
I'd say that Team B probably has the most intelligent members.
(茄子田)Ｂ班はね あの
15人の中でもね➡
めいせき
頭脳明晰なほうを集めたのにね｡
プライドが壁を作るような
この流れは➡
I suppose that you'd expect
that pride would get in the way.
わりと予想通りでは
ありますが…｡
Now, now...
これからどうなるかはね➡
We can't be sure how things will turn out.
まだわかんないよ うん｡
パソコンの打ち込みにね➡
You have the typing test and the Running Math.
計算ランニングと まあ単純作業の
繰り返しによるストレスでね➡
These simple tasks can cause stress to build up...
必ずみんな辛くなってくるからね｡
It will only get worse for them.
Oh, no.
へっ!?どうしたの？
Huh? What's wrong?
What happened?
何 何？うん？
(試験官)福田さんのメガネが…｡
Fukuda's glasses...
(福田)《どうしよう…》
What do I do?
I-It wasn't on purpose!
(古谷)お 俺 ワザとちゃうで！➡
足元にメガネ落ちてるなんて
普通思わへんって！ありえへん！
How was I supposed to know your glasses were on the floor?
That's totally random!
気にしなくていいよ｡古谷君｡➡
You shouldn't worry about it, Furuya.
悪いのは私だから｡
見えますか？福田さん｡
It was my own fault.
Can you see, Fukuda?
管制から ご家族に
電話してもらって➡
We can ask Mission Control
新しいメガネ 送って
もらったほうがいいですよね｡
to contact your family for a new pair.
うん…いや 大丈夫だよ｡
No, that's okay.
It won't make much of a difference.
[TV](福田)なくても
大して影響はない｡
(マシンの音声)１５×３２＝？
15 x 32 -
４８０！
480.
The question is read aloud.
《音声があるんだ｡この課題に
視力は必要ない｡落ち着け！》
I don't need my eyes for this task.
Stay calm.
なあ 古谷｡
やっぱ福田さん 辛そうだぜ｡
Hey, Furuya.
Fukuda seems to be struggling.
Why are you telling me this?
だから なんで俺に言うねん？
俺のせいちゃうて｡➡
It wasn't my fault.
ふかこうりょく
不可抗力の出来事や｡
It was a freak accident.
いや そりゃそうかも
しれないけどさ｡
That's true, I guess...
せめて一言謝ったらどうだよ｡
You could at least apologize.
謝ったらメガネ直んのか？
それに俺 悪いと思てへん｡➡
Will an apology fix his glasses?
Besides, I have nothing to apologize for.
An insincere apology isn't worth jack.
紙よりも薄っぺらいもんは
心にもない言動や…っちゅう➡
ある人の教えや｡
俺 正直者やから｡
I say exactly what's on my mind!
がんこもの
《頑固者だろ》
You're just stubborn.
(福田)７０５！
705!
(福田)《あと９日で必ず２人を
選ばなきゃならない｡➡
We have nine days to decide on two members.
若いみんながいる中で 私が
選ばれるために必要なことは➡
What will it take for me to be chosen over my younger teammates?
年を感じさせないこと｡➡
I cannot show my age.
体力も 視力も 記憶力も➡
At the very least,
I have to match them in stamina, eyesight, memory,
りょく
力という字が入るもの
すべてにおいて➡
彼等と同等以上であることが
最低条件！》
and any other physical requirement.
《この２週間だけの 見せかけの
若さでも かまわない！》
For two weeks, I have to pretend to be younger than I am, if necessary.
(音声)終了デス｡20問正解｡
Finish.
Twenty questions answered correctly.
《よし 悪くない｡だが…》
Good, that wasn't too bad.
But...
ははは…ちょっとトイレへ｡
I need to use the restroom.
《いつもより疲れた
苦しいが我慢だ｡息を殺せ》
I feel more tired than usual...
I must endure the pain,
hold my breath...
(福田)今でも走ってるんだ！➡
I'm still running!
休みの日には 英会話だって
ちゃんと行ってる！
On my days off, I practice conversational English.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](元妻)それで？
And?
When will your hard work pay off?
[ｹｲﾀｲ]その努力が報われる日は
いつ来るのよ｡
Development was halted on the manned rocket you spent all your time on.
[ｹｲﾀｲ]あなたがあれほど
打ち込んできた有人ロケｯトの➡
開発は中止｡この前の
宇宙飛行士採用試験だって➡
And you failed the last astronaut selection exam.
受からなかった｡
あれは…｡
That was...
あなたは一生懸命だったかもしれ
ないけど でも 今まであなたが➡
I'm sure you're doing your best,
but you haven't accomplished a single thing.
やりたかったこと
何ひとつ叶ってないじゃない｡
これから…
これから叶えるんだよ！
Just wait...
It's going to happen!
しじゅう
[ｹｲﾀｲ]４０の男が…
子供みたいな夢見すぎ｡
A forty-year-old man shouldn't cling to dreams like a child.
私は諦めないぞ！➡
I won't give up!
I'll apply for the next selection exam!
次の宇宙飛行士選抜試験がきたら
また受ける！
[ｹｲﾀｲ]涼子には父親が必要なの｡➡
Ryoko needs a father.
夢が叶ったときには
あなた 何歳かしらね？➡
When you've finally realized your dream, how old will you be?
その頃には もう涼子は大人だわ｡
By then, Ryoko will be grown.
現在
Fifty-four, huh?
５４か…｡
I wonder
《涼子は こんな私のことを
どう思ってたんだろうか？》
how Ryoko felt about me...
(元妻)⦅涼子ね 陰山さんのこと➡
Ryoko has started calling Kageyama "Dad".
お父さんって
呼ぶようになってきたのよ⦆
(元妻)⦅せめて夕食くらい
とって行けないの？➡
Can't you stay for dinner first?
You need to have dinner with Ryoko once in a while.
たまには涼子と
ご飯を食べてやってよ⦆
⦅すまない｡私の帰りを
部下達が待っているんだ⦆
Sorry...
My subordinates are waiting for my return.
(涼子)⦅あ…⦆
Bye, Ryoko.
⦅じゃあ涼子
お父さん 行ってくるからね⦆
I'm heading out.
⦅お父さん 今度は
いつ帰ってくるの？⦆
Dad, when will you be back?
⦅お仕事が終わったらね⦆
When I've completed my work.
⦅ゆ～じんロケット できたら？⦆
When the manned rocket is done?
⦅うん そうだよ｡
もうすぐだから⦆
Yep, that's right.
We're almost done.
⦅もうすぐって 明日？⦆
Does that mean you'll be back tomorrow?
Uh, probably not tomorrow.
⦅う～ん 明日はできないなぁ⦆
⦅じゃ 明日の明日？⦆
Then the day after tomorrow?
⦅明日が た～くさん
来たら…かなぁ⦆
It'll probably be a lot of tomorrows...
(福田)⦅ごめんな 涼子｡➡
I'm sorry, Ryoko.
I'll try my best to come home sooner.
お父さん 頑張って
早く帰ってくるから⦆
⦅ごめんよ ごめんよ涼子⦆
Sorry...
Sorry, Ryoko.
⦅プフッ キャハハハ…！⦆
Once I'm done with work, I'll spend a lot of time with you.
⦅休みになったら
うんと遊ぼうね！⦆
That's a promise!
(涼子)⦅じゃ やくそく！⦆
(福田)⦅うん やくそく！⦆
Yep, a promise.
(福田)《約束は一度も
守ってやれなかった》
I didn't keep a single promise I made.
Fukuda
《だが涼子 信じてほしい》
But, Ryoko, I want you to understand...
I never forgot about you.
《父さんは 君を
忘れていたわけじゃないんだ｡➡
ただ…父さんは この夢に➡
I just wanted...
全てをかけて
挑みたかったんだ！》
to give my dream my best effort.
"My Dream", by Fukuda Naoto, class 6-2.
｢僕の夢 ６年２組 福田直人➡
僕の将来の夢は 日本で初めての
有人ロケットをつくって➡
"My dream is to make Japan's first manned rocket,
and to ride it into space."
そして それに乗って
宇宙へ行くことです｣｡
Chin up.
《胸を張れ｡ここまで来たんだ｡➡
I've made it this far.
自分の年なんて忘れよう！➡
No reason to worry about my age now.
My dream
私の夢は
年を取っていない！》
hasn't aged a day!
《くっそ…足の裏…》
Damn, the sole of my foot...
《あの感触 まだ残っとる…》
...still feels that crunch.
(鶴見)福田さん だいぶ
無理してるみたいですね｡➡
Fukuda is pushing himself pretty hard.
メガネ…福田さんの
視力検査のデータあるんで➡
We have Fukuda's prescription,
新しいの用意しましょうか？
so we can order a new pair of glasses.
いや…｡
No.
福田君はね 昔から逆境に
強い男だ｡まだ大丈夫だろう｡
Fukuda's always been strong under pressure.
He should be fine.
まあ それよりね
こういうことが きっかけで➡
Anyway, I'm more interested in seeing how it affects the other team members.
彼らに どういう変化が起こるか➡
もう少し 様子が見たいね｡➡
What will happen?
どうなるかね…
これ 味薄いね｡
This has no taste...
わかってるやろうな｡
やっさんやぞ｡やっさん｡
Got it?
My name's Ya! Ya!
アクセントは｢さ｣の所や｡
You gotta be polite!
わかったって｡
I get it already.
２分経過～｡
Two minutes have passed.
風呂空いたぞ～｡あ？
I'm done with my bath.
They're wagering what each will call the other.
(福田)名前の呼び方を
賭けてるらしいよ｡
Oh.
俺が勝ったら
ムッちゃんだからな｡
If I win, you call me Mu!
アクセントは｢ム｣！
Emphasize the Mu!
これは ただの賭けとちゃう｡
This is no ordinary bet...
どっちが宇宙飛行士に
ふさわしいか➡
This is a battle to determine
ちょっとでも
ゆうれつ
優劣つけとくためのバトルや！
who would make a better astronaut.
え!?それ初耳！
What? I didn't hear anything about that.
(新田)あ～あ…宇宙には➡
There isn't any gravity in space,
上も下も重力ないから
逆立ちの能力いらないだろ｡
so the ability to stand on your hands won't help.
(古谷)逆立ちの能力とちゃう！➡
This isn't about the ability to stand on our hands.
忍耐力と精神力｡
腕力とバランス感覚｡
This tests our bodies and minds, our arm strength and sense of balance!
And how well we can talk with blood rushing to our heads.
あと 頭に血が集まった時の
りょく
スピーチ力！
《全部 初耳…》
He never mentioned any of that.
It's been one week since the third exam began.
《３次試験が始まって１週間…｡➡
ようやく半分が
終わったわけだが➡
We're halfway through.
And everyone's beginning to wonder how we'll make our final selections.
そろそろみんな 誰をどうやって
選ぶのか 気にし始めている》
I've tried analyzing each of the members.
《ここで私は…私なりに
このメンバーを分析してみた》
ギャー！
《京都大学の霊長類研究所で
チンパンジーの習性を➡
Furuya Yasushi has been studying chimpanzee behavior at the Kyoto University Primate Research Institute.
研究してきたという 古谷やすし》
《サルを真似てか
逆立ちの手はグー》
I guess he's doing a handstand on his fists because he's imitating the chimps.
⦅ジブン サル以下やな⦆
You're worse than a monkey.
《…が 俺に対する口癖》
I get that from him all the time.
《｢小さい｣という単語に
過剰に反応する習性あり》
He tends to overreact to the word "small".
Could you make this a little smaller?
⦅ここんとこを
もうちょっと小さく…⦆
⦅誰が小さいって!?⦆
I'm not small!
２分５０秒｡
Two minutes and fifty seconds.
《伊東せりかさんは
逆さに見ても やっぱり美人》
Itou Serika
is still beautiful, even upside-down.
《その上 料理が
すこぶる上手い》
And she's a really good cook.
⦅うまい！⦆
Delicious.
《ただ 量が…ハンパない》
⦅多っ！⦆
But she always makes a ton.
《ごはん粒が よくついている》
And she usually has rice stuck to her face.
⦅フフッ⦆
《筑波大学でスポーツ医学を
れいじ
専攻していたという新田零次》
Nitta Reiji mastered in sports medicine at the University of Tsukuba.
(音声)⦅終了デス｡３８問正解⦆
Finish.
Thirty-eight questions answered correctly.
⦅また俺の勝ちだな
お兄ちゃん⦆
I win again, big brother.
《スポーツ心理を研究し➡
He studied sports psychology, so he's well-versed in mental training.
メンタルトレーニングに
精通している》
《剣道５段の剣士だからか➡
Maybe it's because he's a 5th level kendo master,
いつでも戦える体勢で
落ち着き払っている》
but he always seems to exude calm.
《たまに チラチラと浮き出た
血管を見せてきやがる》
And sometimes, he'll let you see the veins bulging in his arms.
⦅フッ！フンッ‼⦆
《でも トイレ長い》
But he takes forever in the restroom.
《福田直人さんはタフな５４歳》
Fukuda Naoto is a tough fifty-four year old.
《機敏な動作と よく通る声｡
全く年を感じさせない》
He's shrewd, and he speaks in a loud, clear voice.
You'd never know how old he is.
《ロケット開発で
指揮を執ってきた立場にあり➡
At one point, he was in charge of rocket development, which is why he has a strong sense of responsibility and leadership.
責任感が強く頼りになる
リーダー的存在だ》
《頑固な短髪の寝グセと
毎朝 格闘している》
He spends every morning fighting his stubborn hair.
《ただ…メガネが割れて
２日目の今日➡
However...
Two days after his glasses were broken,
とうとう打ち込みテストの成績が
過去最低の結果となった》
his typing test results have reached rock bottom.
じゃあ 先にお風呂もらうよ｡
２人とも頑張って｡
Well, I'll take a bath now.
Good luck, guys.
あ…はい…｡
Oh, right...
(古谷)忍耐力 精神力 腕力
バランス その他もろもろ➡
Physical strength, mental strength, arm strength, balance, etc.
チンパンジー以下やな ジブン｡
You're worse than a chimpanzee in every category.
ハァ ハァ ハァ…｡
パーがグーに負けた…｡
Paper lost to rock...
サルに教わってん｡➡
The monkeys taught me...
パーより手首曲げんでいい
グーの方が力が持続するって｡➡
that rock uses less energy because you don't need to twist your wrist.
まあ 実は
かなり練習してんけどな｡
Well, I've actually trained a fair amount.
勝ちは勝ちや｡やっさんやで｡
But a win is a win.
From now on, I'm Ya.
じゃあ訊くけど やっさん…｡
Then, Ya...
サルが他人のメガネを
間違って壊した場合➡
What would a monkey do after it had accidentally broken
奴らは どうすんの？
someone else's glasses?
アホか｡サルは
メガネせ～へんやろ｡
Moron...
Monkeys don't wear glasses.
福田さんは
平気そうに見せてるけど➡
Fukuda may act like he's fine,
つらそうなのは分かってるだろ？
but you can tell that he's suffering, right?
確実に 課題の
作業効率も落ちてるし｡
And his performance has been dropping.
だけど 俺らは
ある意味 敵同士だから➡
But we're rivals,
手助けするのも
何か違うよな｡
so it wouldn't make sense to help him.
今…福田さんは不利だよ｡
Fukuda is at a disadvantage right now.
(古谷)俺らにとっては
好都合なことやろ｡
All the better for us.
まあ…そうだけど…➡
Well, that's true...
何か あれだろ？
楽しめないだろ これじゃ｡
But you know...
It's no fun this way.
言っとくけど 俺はあの人
別に不利やとは思わへん｡
Let's be clear.
I don't think he's at a disadvantage.
(古谷)ハンデつけて ようやく今
水平ラインや｡➡
Huh?
With his handicap, the playing field is level.
だって あの人
ロケット造ってた時➡
I mean, when he was developing rockets, he worked alongside JAXA bigwigs.
ＪＡＸＡのお偉いさん達と共同で
働いてるんやで｡仲間や 仲間｡➡
He's already buddies with them.
｢公平なる審査｣みたいな話
試験官達も➡
The judges are probably trying to be impartial,
わきまえてるんやろうけど
それでも みんな人間や｡➡
but they're only human.
おっちゃんに対する
尊敬やら恩義やらある人も➡
Some of them probably respect or feel indebted to him.
中には おるやろ 実際｡➡
役職的な強み持ってる時点で
最初から俺らより有利やねんて｡
He started with an advantage through his connections.
Uh...
それちょっと…違います｡
I don't think that's exactly true.
Huh?
私 バスの時に
聞いたんですけど…｡
When I spoke with Fukuda on the bus...
When the astronaut selection exam was announced,
⦅福田さん 今回の宇宙飛行士の
募集が発表された時➡
すぐに会社を
辞められたそうです｡➡
Fukuda immediately quit his job.
今の地位も捨てられるほど➡
He was willing to sacrifice his current life
今回の選抜に
かけてるんだと思います⦆
for a chance at selection.
《アホな おっちゃんやで…｡➡
That old timer's a fool.
辞めるか？普通…》
Who would quit their job?
《ほんま アホやわ…》
He's such a fool...
Uh...
管制室の深夜担当官の皆さん
お疲れ様です｡➡
I'd like to thank the Mission Control night shift staff for their hard work.
これ 見えますか？
Can you read this?
Please order Fukuda new glasses.
下手な字で すんません｡
Sorry about the bad handwriting.
Please order Fukuda new glasses.
なぁんや…➡
Oh...
こんなことで 消えんのかい｡
That's all it took to chase it away?
The lens inside my eyes
went completely out of focus when I saw you
The signs of love flooded the occipital lobe of my cerebrum
The words the left side of my brain produced
brought my vocal cords to reverberation
Vigorously my confession traversed my tongue
May I love you?
May I really love you?
May I be beside you? (The concentration of my hormones rose)
(Dopamine overwhelmed me)
Can I hold your hand? (My blood circulation powered up)
＜閉鎖環境での
宇宙飛行士選抜試験が続く中➡
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#15 Let's Talk About Space
As we continue the astronaut selection in our sealed environment,
またもや 大事件が起こる｡
日々の課題に欠かせない時計が➡
there's another big incident!
Someone dismantled the clock, which we depend on to carry out our daily tasks!
誰かの手によって
バラバラに壊されたのだ＞
(古谷)＜誰やねん 時計壊した奴｡
伊東さんちゃうん？＞
Who took apart the clock?
Was it you, Itou?
＜えっ 私!?＞
Me?!
＜みんなが
疑いの目を向け合う中➡
While everyone is busy suspecting one other,
私だけは
本当の犯人に気付いていた＞
I figure out the real culprit!
＜どうして
あんなことをしたんだ？＞
Why would you do that?
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Let's Talk About Space"
＜もっと
宇宙飛行士気分でいこうぜ＞
We should act more like astronauts.
ひびと
(日々人)パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真です！
スッゲー！
Awesome!